Hi again, there are a few key ways
that project managers help build high-
functioning teams who work
together to meet project goals.
They create systems that
turn chaos into order;
They communicate and listen; they
promote trust and psychological safety;
they demonstrate empathy and
create motivation;
they delegate responsibility and
prioritize; and
they celebrate team's success.
Let's go through each of
those points one by one.
Good project managers lead their teams
by creating systems that turn chaos
into order.
You can do this by creating,
implementing, and improving: standardize,
measurable, repeatable and scalable
workflows and processes for your team.
For example, if you find that you're
usually chasing down teammates for
progress on their work,
you might set up a process for how and
when a teammate should let you know
that they've completed a task.
Think of creating systems as
a kind of connect the dots puzzle.
Being a project manager is sort of
like that, but there are no numbers,
just dots and a partial image.
But we don't need the numbers.
We can notice the dots,
know their importance and
string them together to help everyone
visualize the project as a whole.
You find the system through the chaos and
help other people to find it, too.
Another way that project managers lead
is through communicating and listening.
As the project manager, it's your job
to ensure that everyone on your team
is on the same page regarding
the status of your project.
For example, you might communicate
with the team via daily or
weekly status update emails and
regular team meetings.
Team meetings also provide a space for
listening,
whether you're gathering feedback
on a workflow or process, or
fielding questions from the group.
You can also solicit feedback or
questions via status update emails,
since some people might feel more
comfortable speaking in private.
In addition to communicating and
listening to the wider team,
it's also your responsibility to regularly
connect with individual teammates.
You do this by gaining an understanding
of communication styles and
by asking people on your team
how they prefer to communicate.
What's important to know is that
everyone communicates differently.
For example, I might make small talk
with colleagues who I know enjoy it.
Or I might get straight to the point
with colleagues who prefer not to chat.
Project managers also lead by promoting
trust and psychological safety within
their team.
As a reminder, psychological safety
refers to an individual's perception of
the consequences of taking
an interpersonal risk.
Team members need to trust that they're
safe and speaking up if they have feedback
or concerns about the project as a whole
or about their individual tasks.
It's your job to create a team atmosphere
where different opinions are welcome, and
all members remain respectful of one
another during challenging conversations.
For example, during weekly status
meetings, you might schedule time for
open, thoughtful and
inclusive discussions.
You might model this by asking for
help solving a problem
that's impacting the team.
You should encourage contributions
from all team members regardless of
role or rank.
By doing this, you make clear to
your teammates that they should feel
comfortable challenging processes and
workflows.
And you make clear that critiques of
the project and plans are welcomed and
valued no matter who they come from.
While it can feel challenging
to provide and accept feedback,
it's a healthy part of project
management and usually makes for
a better project outcome.
On an individual level, project
managers lead by practicing empathy and
creating motivation for
their team members.
It's possible you've heard the phrase,
"there's no I in team,"
and while that's true that teams need
to work together to be effective,
it's also important to remember that teams
are made up of individuals with differing
motivations and lives outside of work.
You can demonstrate empathy for your
teammates by being present, listening, and
asking questions.
During one on one conversations,
avoid making assumptions about what
the other person is thinking and feeling.
If you're quiet and curious,
there's always more to learn.
In addition to showing empathy for my
team, I also like to create motivation by
recognizing a job well done
through public forums.
Like in a meeting or a group email.
Recognition tells people that
they're doing the right things, and
motivates them to keep up the good work.
Be sure to recognize good work,
and not just heroic efforts.
Project managers also lead by delegating
responsibility and prioritizing.
Most projects will likely have multiple
tasks taking place simultaneously.
And it's your job to keep the team focused
and heading toward the project goals and
deliverables.
By delegating responsibility for specific
tasks to individuals on your team,
you provide your teammates
with the opportunity to
add value using their
particular set of skills.
You also give yourself space to
focus on the project as a whole.
By prioritizing tasks, you reduce
ambiguity and provide clarity for
your team.
If you think that a task is important,
but your team doesn't,
they might work on
whatever tasks they like.
By prioritizing and
making that prioritization known,
you keep the team focused.
Work with your team to build consensus
around priorities, explaining your
rationale can help you get their buy-in
and increase their commitment to the work.
Lastly, project managers lead
by celebrating team success,
both at the end of the project and
throughout it.
This includes celebrating big and
small wins like reaching a milestone or
receiving positive feedback
from stakeholders.
Celebrating success is
an important tool for
motivating the team because it increases
morale and boosts the team's engagement.
You might celebrate the team with
a group lunch, a small gift or
even just a congratulatory email.
Simple gestures like these demonstrate
appreciation for the team's hard work.
And when people feel appreciated,
they tend to work harder and
their teams perform better.
To recap, project managers build high
functioning teams in a few key ways:
creating systems that turn chaos into
order; communicating and listening;
promoting trust and psychological safety;
demonstrating empathy and
creating motivation; delegating
responsibility and prioritizing; and
celebrating team success.
As you grow in your career, you'll
strengthen your ability to lead bigger and
more complex teams, but the principles
of teamwork will remain the same.
Coming up, you'll learn about
the stages of team development and
how to manage team dynamics.
I'll see you soon.